Okay, בוקר טוב *Boker Tov*, גוט מועד *Gut Moed*, גוט הושענא רבה
Hoshana Rabba, *Gut Hoshana Rabba*, גמר חתימה טובה tovah *Gmar Chatima Tova*
to everyone
and today's דף *daf* is דף ד *Daf Daled*, four, but we
pick up at the very bottom of ג עמוד ב amud bet.
*Gimel Amud Bet* and the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says איבעית אימא *Iba'it
Eima* two lines from the bottom. Some of the things that we
have discovered in the last few days is number one the word
פטור patur. *patur* in the משנה Mishnah: *Mishna* means it's still a
rabbinic problem; number two, in terms of in terms of where the
object is, if an object is on your person and you are
stationary then the object is considered to be in the domain that
you are in. For example, I think maybe a good way to
think about that would be you become like a piece of the
furniture; it's on you, it's like it's on the table. And then
when you move, you are picking it up also off the table,
you are removing it from the domain, which is as I said,
the principle that if you find yourself walking on שבת Shabbos, *Shabbos*
outside of an עירוב *eiruv* and having something on your person, don't
stop, because then it's like you put it down. Then when you
move, it's like you picked it up. Okay, thank you. That is
when it is on your person and you are stationary.
However, if it is on your hand and according to the way
תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* mostly understands the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, your person is
in one place and your hand is in another, your person is
in one domain, your hand is in another, your person is in
רשות היחיד reshut ha-yachid. *reshut hayachid*, your hand in רשות הרבים reshus
harabbim *reshut harabim* let's say in the street, your hand is into
the house and the object is in your hand, or vice versa,
then it is neither considered to be in the house because
you're outside the house, neither is it considered to be outside the
house because you're in the house. So in that case the object
is neither considered to be at rest in the place it is
or in the place where you are, it is in this some
type of indeterminate or middle zone and the whole question of the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* in that case is because it's in this middle
zone when your hand is stuck out and the object is in
your hand, do we let you pull your hand back in? Let's
say you put some food in your hand and you stuck it
outside the window on שבת Shabbos *Shabbos* without an עירוב *eiruv* and
it's now over the airspace of רשות הרבים reshus harabbim, *reshut harabim*,
which we also found out only goes up to עשרה טפחים tefachim.
*asara tefachim*, so now it's neither in the private domain because your
hand is outside, it's neither in the public domain because your person
is inside, do we let you bring it back in to your
house? So we had two ברייתות *braitot*, one said yes, one said
no. The גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* yesterday had some interpretations which had to
do with whether and which cases do we make a קנס knas.
*knas*, which cases we don't make a קנס *knas*, and now we
are wrapping that up. Two lines from the bottom on ג עמוד
ב *Gimel Amud Bet*. איבעית אימא *Iba'it Eima*, if you want you
can say לעולם לא קנסו *le'olam lo knasu*, we did not find
a person who stuck out his hand בשוגג be-shogeg, *beshogeg*, unintentionally, to
prevent him from bringing his hand back in. ולא קשיא *Velo kashya*,
and it's not a difficulty: כאן לאותו חצר chotzer כאן לחצר אחרת
*Kan le'oto chatzer kan lachatzer acheret*. The question is when we say
can you bring the food that's stuck out of the window, can
you drop it now in your yard or in your house, the
question is which yard are you dropping it to? If you pull
it back in to your house, so then you just reversed your
action. We would let you do that; we would let you just
reverse what you had done. Then the net term you hadn't done
anything. However, we would not let you if your hand is now
stuck into רשות הרבים reshut ha-rabim *reshut harabim*, bring it to a
next-door neighbor's yard and drop it in the next-door neighbor's yard. Okay,
as the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says right: כי דבעי מיניה רבה מרב
נחמן *Ki d'ba'ei minei Rabba meRav Nachman*, like Rabba asked Rav Nachman:
היתה ידו מלאה פירות *Haita yado mele'ah peirot*,
the hand was filled with fruit והוציאה לחוץ *vehotzi'ah lachutz*, and he
took it out of his house, you extend your arm and it's
now suspended over רשות הרבים reshut harabim. *reshut harabim*. מהו להחזירה לאותו
חצר *Mahu lehachzirah le'oto chatzer*? Can you return it, pull it back
in to your yard to where you are? אמר ליה מותר *Amar
lei mutar*, it's permissible. לחצר אחרת מאי *Lachatzer acheret mai*, how about
to a different yard? ואמר ליה אסור *Ve'amar lei assur*, you can't.
ומאי שנא *U'mai shena*, what's the difference? In either case you brought
it, you know, it was in this middle zone, the airspace over
רשות הרבים reshut harabim. *reshut harabim* but in your hand so it
was neither רשות הרבים reshut harabim *reshut harabim* nor רשות היחיד reshut
hayachid. *reshut hayachid*. So what difference does it make if you bring
it into your רשות היחיד reshut hayachid. *reshut hayachid* or you bring
it into another one? So he answered: לכי תיכול עלה כורא דמלחא
*Lechi tichol ala kura d'malcha*, first weigh out for me a lump
of salt. Okay, this is a little idiomatic expression in the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* which רש"י Rashi *Rashi* sometimes says means it's like a
little bit of a joke meaning, you know, do some menial task
for me and then I'll tell you. Like it's a way of
maybe putting somebody in a place for asking maybe not such a
good question or maybe it's just a סתם *stam* joke. The other
explanation רש"י Rashi, *Rashi* says that it really means you know why
don't you think about it a little bit and then you'll figure
out the answer, like the time it takes to, you know, measure
out some salt if you sit over a pile of salt on
I don't know some idiom, who knows what the idiom means. But
anyway, weigh it out, right, you know, spend some time with it
and then you'll figure it out. What's the difference? התם Hasham, לא
איתעביד מחשבתו הכא איתעביד מחשבתו *Hatam lo it'avid machshavto hacha it'avid machshavto*.
In the case where you pull it back your intention wasn't satisfied,
nothing was satisfied, we basically had you reverse your action, you're back
to where you started from. That we'll let you do. But to
have you place it somewhere else, you took it out of your
house to איסור *issur* and in the end it winds up somewhere
else out of your house, you actually have accomplished something. Now maybe
not all of what you wanted. Maybe you wanted it in רשות
הרבים, reshut harabim, not on your next-door neighbor's house, but at least
part of what you wanted to, because it's no longer in your
house. Okay? So the end result of all of this is that
there are some cases that we would actually fine you, some cases
not, but as opposed to the גמרא Gemara which had the possibility
that we'd have you have your arm sticking outdoors and having it
there all of שבת, Shabbos, which seems a little bit extreme for
a fine and runs the risk that you would just drop it
in רשות הרבים reshut harabim, and actually do a biblical transgression, according
to this, we say, no, really you're allowed to pull it back,
at least if you're שוגג. shogeg. Maybe you can't drop it in
the next-door neighbor's house, but you can at least pull it back.
But, at least to שוגג, shogeg, it's not so clear by מזיד,
meizid, certainly the גמרא Gemara is seriously considered by מזיד meizid we
might ask you to keep your arm stretched out the whole time,
even if it could end with you dropping it and actually transgressing.
And now the גמרא Gemara is going to return to that issue,
because that is the same case of the bread in the oven.
How much are we concerned that a rabbinic prohibition or restriction will
lead to a biblical transgression? Yes, Michael?
So this is an interesting question, like let's say a שבת Shabbos
case, I'm out there with my wallet in רשות הרבים, reshut harabim.
right? And, you know, there's... there's my neighbor's, you know, house which
is like right next to...
All right, I'm not going to get off track with הלכה halakhah
right now. I mean we have a lot more...
No, no, but basically point is like doesn't it all depend on
which חצר is closer? Like let's say...
No. No. Yes, Charlie, yes?
No, never mind.
Okay, fine. All right, so let's continue now in the גמרא. Gemara
גופא. Gufa. So let's go back to the case about the bread
in the oven. בעי רב ביבי בר אביי, Ba'ei Rav Bibi bar
Abaye, or
רב ביבי Rav Bibi asked אביי Abaye the famous case: הדביק פת
בתנור. hidbik pas b'tanur. Somebody stuck the dough on the walls of
an oven to bake. Now, by שבת, Shabbos you don't transgress as
soon as you put something on the fire. The thing has to
cook. Now, there actually is an interesting question, which is, when is
your action considered to be completed? Let me give you, for example,
let me give you an interesting case. Let's say you put something
on the fire ten minutes before... before שבת Shabbos, was over. And
it only cooked Saturday night after שבת Shabbos? was over. Have you
been מחלל שבת? mechalel Shabbos? Are you considered to be מחלל שבת
mechalel Shabbos by the act of putting it on the fire on
the condition that eventually it cooks? And if it eventually cooks even
hours later, even if it finished cooking after שבת, Shabbos we look
back and we say, ah, that act of putting it on the
fire was considered an act of cooking by virtue of the fact
that eventually it cooked, but is that one act, and that was
done on שבת? Shabbos. Or do we say, no, you're only חייב
chayav on the fact it continues to cook and your continue... your
initial act is considered to continually have been part of the ongoing
process because you began it, and when it finishes cooking you're חייב
chayav but because you cooked on שבת Shabbos and because it finished
cooking on שבת. Shabbos. So the question would be, as I said,
you put on the fire ten minutes before שבת Shabbos, is over,
it finishes after שבת. Shabbos. Have you been מחלל שבת mechalel Shabbos
or not? Now, there's one case, not for cooking, where we know
that it has to finish afterwards. And that is a point that
the רש"ש Rashash makes, which is that when you plant a seed,
you're חייב chayav but the seed has to ultimately take root. It
takes about two weeks for it to take root according to הלכה.
halakhah. So he says there, clearly, it finished... you know, the... what's
needed happens after שבת, Shabbos, but it didn't... it didn't take root
on שבת. Shabbos. And nevertheless, the act of placing the seed in
the ground is what is the transgression on the condition that eventually
it's not a meaningless act, eventually it takes root. If somebody plucked
the seed out after שבת, Shabbos you wouldn't have transgressed, but it's
the act of placing it on the ground. So in theory you
could ask the same question, right, about cooking. The general assumption is
that it has to finish cooking on שבת. Shabbos,
But it's not necessarily so clear. So therefore, here you have now,
I say, just wanted to get you to think that in the
back of your head, which is, what is the act of transgression?
Is it fully just the putting it on the oven, parenthesis, on
the condition eventually it finishes cooking, or is the act of transgression
the fact that it actually cooked and that you were considered to
be involved in that process and the actual cooking took place on
שבת Shabbos. as well? So here's the case, so just have that
in mind. Here's the case where you put the dough on the
wall of the oven. So now, if you leave things on the...
the natural course of events it will finish... it will bake on
שבת, Shabbat, and you will have transgressed. Are you allowed to remove
it before it has finished baking to save yourself from the transgression?
Normally removing bread from an oven that's baked in an oven is
not a מלאכה, melachah, it's not a biblical transgression, but it is
rabbinically forbidden. It's considered to be a חכמה, chochmah, a type of
a skilled labor, okay, which is maybe a little bit too much
like the world of business or whatever. So you're not normally allowed
to, but here if you don't let me do it, I'll wind
up having been מחלל שבת. mechalel Shabbos. Please let me remove it
so that I can save myself from having violated שבת. Shabbos, So
do we let me or not? So let's take a look. בעי
רב ביבי בר אביי: Ba'ei Rav Bibi bar Abaye: הדביק פת בתנור,
hidbik pas b'tanur, somebody stuck bread in an oven. התירו לו לרדותו
קודם שיבא לידי איסור חטאת או לא התירו לו? hitiru lo lirdoto
kodem sheyavo lidei issur chatas o lo hitiru lo?
Should they allow me to remove it before I came to being
obligated in a חטאת, chatas, to violating שבת, Shabbos? or not? אמר
ליה רב אחא בר אביי לרבינא: amar lei Rav Acha bar Abaye
l'Ravina:
היכי דמי? heichi dami? What's the case? אי נימא... iy eima... אי
נימא בשוגג, iy neima be-shogeg, when I put the dough in the
oven—brother? What? I get it.
What's the case? When I put the dough in the oven.
Did I do it בשוגג, b'shogeg. unintentionally, meaning I didn't realize it
was forbidden to do on שבת, Shabbos. I forgot it was שבת?
Shabbos! So my act was a
שוגג shogeg ולא ידעי ve-lo yadei and now I don't remember what
I've done wrong, meaning I don't remember it's שבת. Shabbos! I put
it in there, I thought it was Friday, and I'm going on
my merry way and I still think it's Friday, I don't even
realize I've done anything wrong. So then who, so who you going
to allow to take it down? You don't even know to ask,
you don't even know you've done anything wrong. ואי, Ve-iy, if that's
the case, למאי התירו? le-mai itiru?
So, so who we going to allow to remove the bread? You
don't think you've done anything wrong. אלא לאו, Ella lav, so it
must be דאדכר ואיפטר. de-adkar ve-iftar. So then you realize: Oh my
God, it's שבת! Shabbos. And now you want to reverse your act.
And that happens very often, it's a real problem. Like somebody walks
into a room, isn't thinking, turns on the light. Oh my God,
it's שבת! Shabbos, And turns it back off.
So here, though, so that's really obviously, you know, you haven't—actually think
you've made things worse, but here you oh my God you remember
and now if we let you remove it, reverse it, you actually
will have saved yourself from having done the מלאכה. melacha. Okay, so
that's the question. But if that's true, says the גמרא, Gemara מי
מחייב? mi mechayiv? Even if we don't let you reverse it, you
would not be obligated in a חטאת. chatas. Why not? והתנן, Ve-hasnan,
we taught in the משנה: Mishna כל חייבי חטאות, kol chayavei chataos,
or all people that are obligated in a חטאת, chatas, a sin
offering, אינן חייבין עד שתהא תחילתן שגגה וסופן שגגה. einan chayavin ad
she-tehei techilasan shegaga ve-sofan shegaga.
They're only חייב chayav if from the beginning to the end they
were unaware. So if you are aware at some point in your
performance of the act
that you are doing something wrong, that you know it's forbidden, then
you don't bring a חטאת. chatas. Okay, חטאת chatas you have to
be unaware the entire time of the transgression of the act. You're
not חייב מיתה chayav misa because you didn't start the act intentionally,
but on the other end you sort of fall between the two
categories. To be חייב מיתה chayav misa you have to begin the
act knowing you're violating and so on. Here you began it unaware,
but you're not חייב חטאת chayav chatas because you didn't finish it
unaware. In the middle of the baking, you remembered that it was
שבת. Shabbos, So the גמרא Gemara says, so then why do we
have to allow you? You wouldn't be חייב חטאת chayav chatas anyway.
Now, it's a funny question because you don't really—look, we're not in
a time where you're bringing sacrifices regardless. So it's not really a
question of are we going to save you from having to bring
a sacrifice? The real question is we want to save you from
violating שבת, Shabbat? whether willfully
or unintentionally. But if we let you reverse it, we'll have saved
you from a violation. So תוספות Tosfot. asks that. Like he doesn't
even understand what's bothering the גמרא Gemara so much. Okay, so you
don't bring a חטאת, chatas, but we still want to save you
from the violation. But somehow the גמרא Gemara, is not ready to
say that. It thinks save means we're saving you from an actual
this-world consequence. So therefore, since you don't have to bring a חטאת,
chatas, why would we have to allow you to remove it, since
because you became aware, you would not be obligated in a sin
offering. That's one issue, and really it has an easier answer available
to itself; for some reason it's not using it. But the other
point is the one I wanted to make to you before. How
do we consider the act of transgression? The fact that it says
if I became aware later that I will not bring a חטאת
chatas because I have not been unaware from beginning to end, pretty
much makes explicit that by cooking, it's considered to be, right, that
the entire process of cooking, even though I only placed it on
the fire for one second, but that I'm considered to be doing
the act the entire process of cooking. If my entire act was
just the placing of the fire, then when I did it I
was totally unaware. The fact that it needs to finish cooking, that's
not the עבירה, aveira, that's just a condition that it wouldn't have
been meaningful if it didn't finish cooking. But me becoming aware later
wouldn't be significant. The fact that my becoming aware later is considered
like I became aware during the transgression sounds like the placing on
the fire is the ongoing cooking that is the act of the
transgression. I'm considered to ongoingly be cooking this object as it is
on the fire. And therefore when I become aware in the middle,
I'm now aware in the middle of the act, and therefore it
is not obligated in a חטאת, chatas, I'm not unaware from beginning
to end.
Yes? Here, it doesn't say from beginning to end, it says the
beginning and the end, which would then
mean—well, but that's—if I'm
aware in the middle then it's—okay, but that's what we mean.
Okay. Okay, so now okay, so the גמרא Gemara. says so yes.
I just wondered if that could be applied to like if you—tomorrow's
יום טוב. Yom Tov. Right. Let's say you wrote a letter and
you mailed it this morning. Is that related in any way?
Well, no, because if you begin something before שבת, Shabbat. there's certainly
not a problem. Now what you actually—what you're saying is a good
question. There's a famous נימוקי יוסף Nimukei Yosef that asks this. He
says that if you're considered to
be ongoingly doing the act as it continues to happen, right? So
he says, I mean, he particularly is basing himself on a גמרא
Gemara in בבא קמא Bava Kamma that says when you light a
fire, it's continuous. burning is like shooting an arrow, it's continuing to
be your action. So he says why when you light a fire
on ערב שבת Erev Shabbat is it not like you're continuing to
make the fire on שבת? Shabbat Okay, so that's a question that
does get asked. But the basic answer is that you cannot violate
unless you've actually actively done something on שבת. Shabbat Anything you've done
before שבת Shabbat. is associated to the pre-שבת Shabbat stay. Okay. Now,
there could be rabbinic things like you're not allowed to let your
food on a fire without a בלעך blech ערב שבת Erev Shabbat
and so on. You know, the rabbi tells us the way you
have to set things up before שבת. Shabbat. But in terms of
violating שבת Shabbos biblically, it's only an act can be done on
שבת. Shabbat If you did something before and then things go by
themselves, that cannot be a biblical violation. Okay. Alright, so now let's
see where the גמרא Gemara continues. It says, okay. So anyway, so
if you become aware in the middle, technically you don't have to
bring a קרבן. korban. So why should we allow you to take
down the bread? אלא במזיד. Ella b'meizid. So okay, you willfully put
the bread up and even so, even though you're here, you were,
you know, really like did a willful violation, maybe we should still
have רחמנות rachmanus on you and now that you had the spirit
of תשובה teshuva came over you, good, you know, הושענא רבה, now
we're still within this period, you had this spirit of תשובה teshuva
came over you, we should allow you to reverse it, even though
you started willfully and you did it במזיד. b'meizid. So that's the
case. Do we allow you to reverse it? קודם שיבא לידי איסור
סקילה מיבעי ליה. Kodem sheyavo lidei issur sekilah miba'ei lei. So it's
interesting to say do we let you reverse it before you come
to be obligated in a קרבן, korban, and it should have said
do we let you reverse it before you become obligated in stoning.
אמר רב שילא... Amar Rav Shila... לעולם בשוגג. l'olam b'shogeg. Really we
are talking about בשוגג. b'shogeg. So, and again, rather than saying that
it's not technically a קרבן, korban, no, it is a קרבן. korban.
You remain completely unaware. ולמאן התירו? Ul'man hitiru? When do we say
do we allow? It means לאחרים. l'acherim. Do we allow your friend
to take it down? You went, you put something in the oven
and you walked your merry way. Okay. And then somebody saw from
a distance, he whatever, by the time he got there you had
left, but he sees the bread baking. So he says I'm going
to do a טובה for that guy, I'm going to take the
bread down in order to save him from doing this חילול שבת
chillul Shabbat and being obligated in a קרבן. korban. He's not even
aware about what he did. So you, the bystander, want to do
this to help this poor guy who did this בשוגג. beshogeg. Do
we allow you to violate דרבנן d'rabbanan in order to save him
from this קרבן? korban? So let's and from this sin. Okay. מתקיף
לה רב ששת, Maskif leh Rav Sheshet, רב ששת Rav Sheshet asks
on this.
וכי אומרים לו לאדם חטא כדי שיזכה חברך? V'chi omrim lo l'adam
cheit b'kdei sheyizkeh chavercha? Do we say to somebody sin in order
to save, help your friend? Now that raises interesting questions, right, about
maybe we, you know, do we or don't we? And I'll talk
in a minute about תוספות. Tosfot תוספות Tosfot says it sounds like
sometimes we actually do say that. But he feels no. Like, you
know, it's true that I have a responsibility to my, to my
fellow, you know, in religious matters. I have, first of all, I
can't cause somebody to sin, לפני עיוור, lifnei iver, מכשול, machshol, we
spoke about that. I even can't be an innocent bystander when somebody
is sinning. I have a חיוב chiyuv of תוכחה, tochacha, of giving,
of you know, of giving remonstrance, of להפרישו מן איסור. l'hafrisho min
issur. I do have a real responsibility to my fellow, you know,
sinning and not sinning as a, you know, as a fellow Jew
and as a shared sense of a commitment to, to תורה Torah
and the מצוות. mitzvot. However, right, it's not, it seems that it
doesn't go so far that I should actually transgress as a result
of you. Okay. Now it's an interesting question in all cases. Meaning
here you were willful. So maybe I could say I'm not going
to transgress to help you for your willful sin. Okay. But let's
say you were unintentional. And maybe I should do a small sin
to save you from a big sin. How do you figure out
that tradeoff? Now it might seem a little cruel, why can't we
let me do a small sin to save you from a big
sin? But you know, if you, if you think about, and I'll
talk about תוספות Tosfot, says about this in a minute, but just
for a moment, if you think about the parallel,
do I have to sacrifice a limb to save your life? Right?
I have to help you, I have to save you if you're
in danger, I have to save you if your, if your limb
is at risk, if any, if any type of injury I have
to help you from. But a general principle is חייך וחיי חברך
חייך קודמין. chayecha v'chayei chavercha chayecha kodmin. You have a first responsibility
to yourself. Right? And even if it's
disproportionate. הלכה Halacha is I don't have to risk a limb to
save your life. Okay. So there's something analogous here about that. Now
it does seem a little bit somehow more problematic when it's about
me concerned about my own religiosity, my, my own transgression, rather than
concerned about my own body, you know, and sometimes that's a big
problem when people are so over-concerned about their own religiosity, you know,
that they forget that being religious also means being concerned about other
people and their welfare as well. So there are those issues that
do come up. So I'll talk in a minute about how תוספות,
Tosfot other questions תוספות Tosfos raises about this. But at least in
this context, the גמרא Gemara is questioning that. Would we let me
do a small sin, even a rabbinic sin, to help you? How
should we allow such a thing? Maybe in parentheses particularly since what
you did was intentional. That's the way the גמרא Gemara phrases it.
Oh, wait, more. You get...
yeah but on the other hand all the more so that... responsibility
to you, you dug your own hole. So let's take a look.
So the גמרא, Gemara so that's at least the challenge. אלא אמר
רב אשי, Ella amar Rav Ashi, says רב אשי, Rav Ashi, we'll
get back to that in a minute, but says רב אשי, Rav
Ashi, לעולם במזיד. le'olam bemezid. Okay.
No, I'm sorry. Oh, no, no, no. I made a mistake because
we had shifted. I'm sorry. We had shifted to שוגג. shogeg. So
in that case actually was שוגג, shogeg, which does make it more,
I think, disturbing. Right, remember we had first said it can't be
במזיד, bemezid, right, because then it should have said איסור סקילה. issur
sekilah. So we went back and we said that it was בשוגג.
beshogeg The guy did it unawares, he walked away, he would be
חייב קרבן, chaiyav korban, and still we're saying why should we let
me do a small sin to save this guy who was unintentional
and בשוגג beshogeg. and would have been חייב קרבן? chaiyav korban? And
that seems a little more disturbing. I mean, נעבעך, nebech, you were
שוגג, shogeg, like you weren't, what you did, I mean obviously you
were to some degree negligent, but that still is the objection in
the גמרא. Gemara רב ששת Rav Sheshet assumes we would not let
one person do a small sin, a דרבנן derabbanan transgression to save
his fellow from having done a חייב חטאת, chaiyav chatas, from being
חייב chaiyav in transgressing שבת Shabbat, בשוגג.
b'shogeg And you're saying קל וחומר kal vechomer to me? I don't
know.
Let's just leave it at that for now. But I do want
to correct, I said it incorrectly, it was the case of שוגג
shogeg and nevertheless רב ששת Rav Sheshet objects and says we would
not let somebody do that. So I'll go back in a minute
to question that, but that's where we are right now. So we've
got to say that we're talking about the person himself. אלא אמר
רב אשי לעולם במזיד. Ella amar Rav Ashi le'olam bemezid. Fine, we
are talking about מזיד. mezid. ואימא, ve'eima, and therefore you're trying to
save yourself. ואימא, ve'eima, so switch the text, don't have it קודם
שיבוא לידי איסור סקילה, kodem sheyavo lidei issur sekilah,
although the original thing was phrased as before you're חייב חטאת. chaiyav
chatas. Okay, doesn't mean it. It means before you're חייב סקילה. chaiyav
sekilah. So we're talking about מזיד. mezid. And therefore can you do
the דרבנן derabbanan to save yourself? רב אחא בריה דרבא מתני לה
בהדיא. Rav Acha brei deRava matni lah behedya. רב אחא Rav Acha
the son of רבא Rava said explicitly this was the way it
was phrased, and also that it wasn't a question, that it was
a conclusion. אמר רב ביבי בר אביי לא בעי, Amar Rav Bibi
bar Abaye lo ba'ei, that's not that רב ביבי בר אביי Rav
Bibi bar Abaye asked, but רב ביבי בר אביי Rav Bibi bar
Abaye said, הדביק פת בתנור, hidbik pas betanur, if he stuck the
bread in the oven, התירו לו לרדותה קודם שיבוא לידי איסור סקילה.
hetiru lo lirdosah kodem sheyavo lidei issur sekilah.
They did allow you to לרדותה. lirdosah. So first of all, it's
not a question, we have a conclusion. They did allow you to
remove the bread. And number two, we're talking about a case of
מזיד. mezid. So you willfully did it, you'd be חייב סקילה. chaiyav
sekilah. So the conclusion is we did allow you to remove the
bread. Now I want to talk about this case, about the conclusion
here and then go back to the issue about אומרין לאדם חטא.
omerin leadam cheit. So first of all, this conclusion is very consistent.
It's even funny that in this context of this discussion the גמרא
Gemara does not bring up a lot of other cases in מסכת
שבת. Masechet Shabbos. Because as I said yesterday, there's a really repeating
theme in שבת Shabbos, that we will often allow you to do
a דרבנן, derabbanan, something that otherwise is rabbinically prohibited because of our
awareness that if we don't let you do it, you'll come to
do a דאורייתא. de'oraissa. You'll come to do a מזיד. mezid. Like
we let you, if you find yourself with your wallet outside of
the city on שבת, Shabbos. and if we don't tell you, give
you a way to do it with rabbinic transgression, you're just going
to carry it and even do a biblical transgression. Or things about
saving objects from a fire and so on that generally we do
understand the human psychology and we're willing to do something so it
doesn't lead to being
חייב חטאת chaiyav chatas or חייב סקילה. chaiyav sekilah. It's funny that
the גמרא Gemara doesn't bring that in here. Maybe you could make
some distinctions there. It's about a new act, it's about a previous
act. Nevertheless, the conclusion of the גמרא Gemara is the same. That
we'll be willing to bend even in the case where you began
with a willful violation, we'll be willing to say forget about the
דרבנן, derabbanan, save yourself from the איסור סקילה, issur sekilah, go ahead
and remove the bread from the oven. Now תוספות Tosfos asks a
very
reasonable
question. He says, I don't get this. This guy willfully put the
bread in the oven. Now he wants to save himself from violating
שבת, Shabbos? he wants to remove it. But we tell him דרבנן,
derabbanan, you're not allowed to do it. So תוספות Tosfos says, who's
going to listen to us? Even if we say you're not allowed
to do it, he's going
to say, "Oh, so now all of a sudden I'm going to
be פרום frum and listen to the דרבנן derabbanan and be חייב
סקילה?" chaiyav sekilah?
Like
what good would it do to say that anyway? So he doesn't
really understand how that could even be a possibility, like what is
going to be the effect of saying that type of a thing?
So maybe the effect would be either way he's going to take
it out, but we want to know if he gets a demerit
or not, if he's transgressed דרבנן derabbanan or not. You know? So
תוספות Tosfos doesn't understand that. But תוספות Tosafot comes up with an
amazing חידוש. chiddush. He says, actually, if we were to say you're
not allowed to remove the bread, then he would not transgress שבת.
Shabbos Because then the reason he was not removing it was because
we wouldn't allow him. It's like we tied his hands together. So
if we've tied his hands together, then he is not actually doing
a מעשה ma'aseh because the end of the act ended באונס, be'ones,
ended against his will. Now notice again that this considers it that
the act of cooking or baking is considered to be an ongoing
act. The initial act was totally willful, but if we tie his
hands at the end and he wants to remove it and we're
not letting it, it's like the end of the cooking was באונס.
be'ones. And part of the obligation goes through the entire act of
cooking.
And that
exists in the sphere... So then the conclusion is even more shocking:
we would rather him to not have done the transgression altogether and
to actively do a דרבנן drabbanan and remove it than to have
not transgressed the דרבנן drabbanan and have done the and have done
the transgression באונס. b'ones. Now you see that's the alternative. Either way
you're not חייב. chayav. But one way you're not חייב chayav because
you haven't actually done the transgression. You stopped the act and you
removed it. And the other way you're not חייב chayav because we
tied your hands together. And in the conclusion we'd rather you actively
violate a דרבנן drabbanan and interrupt the act so that you haven't
actually concluded the act rather than to have to be get off
because you did conclude it but you were אונס. ones. So it's
better to actually interrupt it. So that makes the conclusion even more
powerful how much we want to, you know, save you from חילול
שבת chillul Shabbos even though in the other case it wouldn't have
really been a חילול שבת chillul Shabbos anyway but he tells us
you would have been an אונס. ones. But again it is quite
amazing this idea that it's that the fact that you started the
act and you started it willfully, if we tie your hands in
the middle and you want to reverse it that you're exempt, that's
a תוספות Tosafot says that that's the גמרא Gemara but תוספות Tosafot
says what type of question is that, at what point would there
be, you won't listen to us anyway. Okay now let's go back
to the issue before about do we say that you can violate
in order to save somebody else from sin. So תוספות Tosafot starts
with a couple of examples where it seems like we do allow
you to violate to save somebody from sin. He has an example
where let's say some poor people took some fruit from your field
and if you don't and that wasn't תרומות ומעשרות, terumot u'ma'asrot, there
was נטע רבעי, neta revai, somehow anyway if you don't do a
certain minor דרבנן drabbanan they'll transgress eating fruit that is טבל. tevel.
So and we allow you to do a minor דרבנן. drabbanan. So
why is that okay? So תוספות Tosafot says that's different because there
you're party to the sin. The reason their sin is going to
be they took your fruit from your field. So although you're so
there we let you violate because because if you if they sin
you're you're partly to blame for that so you're responsible for what's
happening in that case. Because you grew fruit? You you grew fruit
and you didn't put up signs and you didn't warn them and
somehow you're party to it. Okay I mean I won't go into
the details of the case but it was a case where somebody
stole the fruit from you okay so they took their תרומות terumot
it was a certain case so anyway so he says so so
so that case is different because there you have a real responsibility
because you were sort of part of the whole process to begin
with but that's different from being a completely third party.
Now but then he says that what I mean another difference hold
on let me just find it.
He there's another difference as well. A difference between stopping somebody from
sinning as opposed to reversing a sin. Okay there's a sort of
like I was saying before שב ואל תעשה shev v'al ta'aseh but
again the גמרא Gemara is talking even about שוגג shogeg but there
still is a difference. In this case by the oven you already
did at least the initial act of sin. Maybe not the whole
act but you began the process and so on. So now the
question is I have you're asking me to violate to help you
reverse something bad that you did. Fine maybe it was שוגג. shogeg.
But you've already done the wrong act. Okay there my responsibility is
a lot less. You already got like somehow dug your hole and
are in your hole. Okay my responsibility is a lot less than
if I can intervene and stop you from sinning. And there maybe
it's very different. There if to intervene to stop you from sinning
then it would be absolutely warranted for me to do it. So
that's a second case תוספות Tosafot says and a third part and
a third distinction he says is one minute
maybe it depends on how whatever one minute
right that the third case is although the case in the גמרא
Gemara isn't מזיד meizid at least it's a case about negligence. What
if it's an example where the person is not to blame at
all? Okay so if somebody is about to somehow sin due to
no fault of their own then someone said well why is it
then a sin why isn't it אונס ones or whatever but sometimes
certain circumstances can happen you know and therefore that's a case where
where you also we would allow you and say you should do
a small violation in order to save somebody from a big one.
So actually there's a contradiction there's a lot of cases in the
גמרא Gemara I'm not giving you the specific cases but there's a
lot of cases where it actually says not only do we allow
you but even says you're supposed to, you have a moral obligation
to do a small sin to save somebody else from a bigger
sin. So you have to line those up side by side by
this statement which says we don't allow you and try to figure
out if there's any consistency are there any rules. But as I
said תוספות Tosafos gives a couple of important points of distinction. Okay
number one is one else I didn't mention it how big is
the sin or how big is the consequence although here the consequence
seems pretty big חילול שבת. chillul Shabbos. But nevertheless sometimes there could
be a huge consequence. Okay number two is the question about are
you already involved and responsible? Number three is
the question about... maybe it's more like they did it to themselves.
And the and the other one, which is also a certain degree
of it's their own fault, is if they were negligent. If they're
willful or negligent, maybe that's different than if they're not willful or
negligent. Look, you can imagine a case where the person isn't willful
or negligent, somehow
where the person is not willful or negligent, okay. Somebody bought something
from a store, you know, that was being sold as kosher and
they're about to put it in their mouth, you know, and I
just found out that that store actually, it was that that animal
was a טריפה treifa or that store got found out it was
selling טריפות treifas like that whole case a year or two ago,
whatever. Anyway, but now in order to get the news to you
and stop you from putting it in your mouth, I would have
to somehow violate a דרבנן d'rabbanan to get that news to you
in time before you're about to stick I can't think of a
case, I'd have to go חוץ לתחום chutz l'tchum or something, I
don't know, whatever some type of a case like that. You can
imagine. So you're about to eat טרייף, treif, okay, but no fault
of your own, so would I be able to intervene if it
meant that I'd have to violate a דרבנן d'rabbanan in order to
intervene and to help you. So the important point is that this
is not at all black and white. There's a lot of cases
where the גמרא Gemara says you're not only allowed to, but you're
obligated to intervene and תוספות Tosafos tries to make distinctions about stopping
before it happens as opposed to once it already began, and also
the degree of responsibility the transgressor himself has. How much he already
began the action and to what degree he was to blame and
negligent as opposed to not to blame.
Yeah, in this particular case over here, then it seems that ההיא
דהדבקת
פת בתנור hahi d'hadbakas pas b'tanur that it really would be you
that should reverse it as opposed to me, right?
Like meaning like well, that's the גמרא Gemara no, the גמרא Gemara
clearly accepts that the person himself has more latitude to do something
to save himself from sin, right? That's why the גמרא Gemara shifted.
Okay, we're not talking about you, we're talking about me. So that's
clearly true that we know that that I have a more right,
you know, to do a small thing to save myself from a
big sin. The question is you, as I said, an interesting analogy
of like giving up your limb to save a life, you know,
thinking about it along those lines. But as I said, that is
a little bit problematic because, you know, unfortunately that's a real problem
when people think that all their tiny little things of their quote-unquote
religiosity are much more important than, you know, their responsibility to other
people, you know, so that's, you know, so obviously that can be
taken way out of proportion. Bobby, what did you want to say?
No, I just wondered if for example, just to give an example,
wondering if this would be an example, let's say someone is ill
for a while and came out of the illness and literally not
aware of the day it is and started to do something that
would violate שבת? Shabbos.
So that would also be a case of? Yeah, exactly, if there's
no negligence about not knowing what day it was, right, they woke
up from a coma or something, right, then clearly, yeah, right, definitely,
yeah.
So I'm just curious about something. He said that it was the
case with שוגג, shogeg, but then they give us the answer
for מזיד. meizid. What's the answer for שוגג? shogeg?
So the גמרא Gemara basically, you're at a good point, the גמרא
Gemara didn't really conclude because of this technical issue about that if
I became aware, you know, I wouldn't be חייב chayav a קרבן
korban anyway. But תוספות Tosafos essentially says, look, even though I wouldn't
be חייב chayav a קרבן, korban, it would still be a transgression
of שבת Shabbat that I wouldn't want to do, so presumably the
answer is like a you know, it's not clear because you could
say maybe they gave me more latitude but מזיד meizid because the
sin was worse, but yes, but the same it seems to be
the thrust is is that I would be allowed, and that seems
to be what תוספות Tosafos, says, although it's interesting that the גמרא
Gemara never really got back to the שוגג. shogeg. What does become
clear is במזיד b'meizid we let me, בשוגג we don't let somebody
else because אין אומרים לאדם חטא כדי שיזכה חברך ein omrim l'adam
chatei k'dei she'yizkeh chaveirecha and you're right the גמרא Gemara didn't conclude
about if me I myself became aware, but תוספות, Tosafos you know,
indicates that that would be the same, that we would we would
let me in that case. Okay, so alright, so now let's take
a look that let's as the גמרא Gemara continues. So that was
a fascinating little topic and now we get back to carrying on
שבת. Shabbat, פשט העני את ידו. Pashat he'ani es yado. So the
עני ani sticks his hand inside the house so and
and picks the bread off the hands of the בעל הבית baal
habayis and brings it out. So then he's done עקירה, akira, הוצאה,
hotza'ah, and הנחה. hanachah. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says אמאי חייב?
amai chayav? Why is he חייב? chayav? ובעינן עקירה והנחה מעל גבי
מקום ארבע על ארבע וליכא. Ve'ba'inan akira v'hanachah mei'al gabei makom arba
al arba v'leika. You need to pick up and put down from
a space that is ארבע על ארבע. arba al arba. Okay, four
by
four roughly. So the idea is is that you are only חייב
chayav when you remove an object that is in a space of
four by four. Now why is that? Like, you know, the Torah
is never really clear about what defines the act of הוצאה, hotza'ah,
where do we get this idea that you need it to be
in a in a place, in an important place of ארבע על
ארבע? arba al arba? So רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot. give different
answers. If you look at רש"י, Rashi מעל גבי מקום ארבע, mei'al
gabei makom arba, רש"י Rashi? says about eight lines before the
line before the end, he says דהוי חשוב למהוי הנחתו הנחה ועקירתו
עקירה. d'havi chashuv l'meihavi hanachato hanachah v'akira-to akira. Okay, וידו לאו מקום
ארבע הוא v'yado lav makom arba hu etc. etc. So רש"י Rashi
says that
that size is it makes it important. it's not the size of
the object. So the removal from the place, there's also the שיעור
shiur of have you done something significant? And what is also being
struggled with here and it's hard at first time to understand, as
I said, הוצאה hotza'ah is not really a creative act. הוצאה hotza'ah
is the hardest מלאכה melacha on שבת to understand, right, it's called
by the ראשונים Rishonim מלאכה גרועה, melacha gerua, so partly we focus
much more on the activity than on the result. And we have
these greater criteria. So in order to give the activity significance, not
only does the object have to be a certain size, but you
have to remove it from a space that you've done something significant.
And one way of thinking about that, what does it mean you've
done something significant, is maybe we're trying to get it a way
of seeing הוצאה hotza'ah as somehow changing something. Not just moving something,
but changing something. So if something is in a space and you've
taken it out of the space, you've somehow changed the nature of
the space. Maybe you've also changed the nature of the object because
it's in a different space, it was in one type of space
and it's in a different type of space. Now that idea seems
more articulated by תוספות. Tosafot תוספות Tosafot quotes a פסוק pasuk אל
יצא איש ממקומו ביום השבת, al yetze ish mi-mekomo be-yom ha-Shabbat, don't
leave ביום השביעי be-yom ha-shevi'i and you don't leave your space, which
has to do with go, maybe you have to go out to
collect the מן, mann, going outside the תחום, techum, but nevertheless one
דרשה drasha has it also don't take your vessels from their space
to collect the מן mann and sees that to be referred to
הוצאה. hotza'ah. And there ממקומו mi-mekomo from your space. So there's an
idea of removing something from its space. It's not just transferring it,
it's taking it out of one space and placing it into another
space. So a space and being in a place is considered to
be in a place of ארבעה. arba'ah. And as I said, maybe
that's getting to this idea of also seeing as some type of
change. You're changing the nature of the space, a space that had
an object, you're changing the object, the object is now in a
different space. So maybe we're trying to get at that, which is
a hard concept by הוצאה. hotza'ah. But somehow the גמרא Gemara takes
it for granted that you're only חייב, chayav, not only do you
need עקירה akira and הנחה, hanacha, it has to start in a
space ארבעה על ארבעה arba'ah al arba'ah and end in a space,
maybe place is a better word than space, and end in a
place ארבעה על ארבעה. arba'ah al arba'ah. And if it's sitting in
your hand, that's no ארבעה על ארבעה, arba'ah al arba'ah, right? So
how are you going to be חייב, chayav, right, in in you
know in that type of a case? So let's take a look
at what the גמרא Gemara says. I should say by the way
in terms of this whole idea of the significance of הוצאה, hotza'ah,
you know I was thinking that in a lot of ways, you
know, most of the development of society is based on the on
הוצאה, hotza'ah, you know it's based on the ability to convey materials
from one place to the other. You know, rivers and railways and
all those types of things, you know, have determined the growth of,
you know, cities and societies, you know, from ancient times. It's all
about conveying objects from one place to another. So it's very important
within that world of activity, the idea of conveyance. But within the
normal way that we normally think about שבת, it lacks this idea
of creative labor, although it is such a central part of the
business of, you know, of society. Anyway, so that's the גמרא's Gemara
question.
Yes. So did we decide yesterday that the hand was a כרמלית
karmelit or is that still an...
No, the hand is neither רשות הרבים reshut harabim, nor רשות היחיד.
reshus hayachid Whether we give it a דין din of a כרמלית,
karmelit, it seems like we don't. It seems like it's some type
of a neither zone and it's only a question about a קנס.
Okay, but still the question is that's when your hand is extended
in a different רשות. reshut. But here we're talking about I stick
my hand in and pick the bread off of your hand. Well
why have I done a מלאכה? melacha? I took it from your
hand and your hand isn't a מקום ארבעה. makom arba'ah. Now conceptually
we are looking about it, it seems to me, when you're holding
the bread in your hand, that we're not saying that's like the
bread is on the ground, we're saying like you are like a
table. So here I am, I'm holding the bread in my hand,
I'm a table, the owner sticks his hand in and picks it
up. So fine, it's like you took it off of a small
little pedestal, but that's not a place of ארבעה על ארבעה, arba'ah
al arba'ah, so why is it enough to be חייב? chayav? Okay?
So let's take a look at what the גמרא Gemara says.
וליכא ve-leika and you don't have it? Says the גמרא Gemara, says
אמר רבא הא מני רבי עקיבא היא. amar Rava ha mani Rabbi
Akiva hi. This הא מני רבי עקיבא, ha mani Rabbi Akiva, this
is רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. דאמר לא בעינן מקום ארבעה על ארבעה.
de-amar lo ba'inan makom arba'ah al arba'ah. So now here though notice
this גרסה girsa is, right, ארבעה על ארבעה arba'ah al arba'ah which
is טפחים. tefachim. Okay, so תוספות Tosafot, said as I said if
you look at תוספות, Tosafot. הא בעינן עקירה והנחה מעל גבי
מקום
ארבעה, ha ba'inan akira ve-hanacha me-al gabei makom arba'ah, he
says מקומו של אדם היינו ארבע אמות. mekomo shel adam hainu arba
amot. Okay, so I'm... he says הא בעינן הנחה מקום ארבעה אמר
רבינו תם דאין רגילות להניח חפץ פחות מארבעה. ha ba'inan hanacha makom
arba'ah amar Rabbeinu Tam de-ein regilut le-hani'ach chefetz pachot me-arba'ah. And then
he says ואור"י דאל יצא איש ממקומו משמע דקא חשיב מקום מקומו
של חפץ, ve-ora"i de-al yetze ish mi-mekomo mashma de-ka chashiv makom mekomo
shel chefetz, דרשינן d-arshinan in
עירובין Eruvin דאל יצא אל יוציא. de-al yetze al yotzi. אף על
גב דקרא קאי אמקומו של אדם דהיינו ארבע אמות af al gav
de-kra kai a-mekomo shel adam de-hainu arba amot משמע נמי מקום כמו
מקומו של חפץ מקום חשוב בפחות מארבעה. mashma nami makom kmo mekomo
shel chefetz makom chashuv be-pachot me-arba'ah. Okay, so it's not exactly clear
from תוספות. Tosafot, He says the מקום makom of an אדם adam
is ארבע אמות, arba amot, then he switches to the מקום makom
of a חפץ. chefetz. So it could be in the end when
he switches back to the מקום makom of the חפץ, chefetz, he
admits that for the object we're talking not about a four by
four אמות amot but
a four by four
טפחים. tefachim? Even if it's on a table. This table is not
ארבע על ארבע אמות, arba al arba amot, right? It's not six
feet by six feet. Okay, so so the so by so even
תוספות, Tosafot it seems like he's actually saying in distinction from the
מקום של אדם makom shel adam and here actually talking about ארבעה
טפחים, arba tefachim, right? That the place has to be in a
place not so—it doesn't have to be in
a—a—like, you know, personal space which is ארבע על ארבע אמות, arba
al arba amot, but somehow the significance of the space of an
object, even for that object to be considered to be in a
space, you know, in its own space and not just
like נשתהה נשתהה, nishta'eh nishta'eh, is that it be in a place
that's ארבעה על ארבעה טפחים, arba'ah al arba'ah tefachim, which is radically
different. ארבעה על ארבעה טפחים arba'ah al arba'ah tefachim is essentially about
a foot by a foot. Okay.
So, like a tray, it is that case. He's holding a tray.
Okay, well the גמרא Gemara will get to that. Okay, so anyway,
that's a very important question. Are we אמות amot or טפחים? tefachim.
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva makes it clear with that גירסא girsa that
we're talking about טפחים. tefachim. דתנן. d'tnan. So anyway, it's רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva because—so where does רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva say you don't
require it?
הזורק מרשות היחיד לרשות היחיד ורשות הרבים באמצע. hazorek mereshut hayachid lereshut
hayachid ureshut harabim be'emtza. Somebody throws an object from a private domain
to a private domain and the public street is in the middle.
רבי עקיבא מחייב וחכמים פוטרים. Rabbi Akiva mechayev vechachamim potrim. Rabbi Akiva
says you've transgressed and the חכמים chachamim exempt. Now, why have you
transgressed according to רבי עקיבא? Rabbi Akiva? The object didn't stop in
the רשות הרבים. reshut harabim It flew straight through the air.
Yeah, under ten טפחים. tefachim, רבי עקיבא סבר אמרינן קלוטה כמי שהונחה
דמיא. Rabbi Akiva savar amrinan kluta k'mi she'huncha damya. Rabbi Akiva says
we say something absorbed sort of by the airspace is like it's
on the
ground. ורבנן סברי לא אמרינן קלוטה כמי שהונחה דמיא. verabanan savri lo
amrinan kluta k'mi she'huncha damya. And the Rabbis say we don't say
that. So basically, Rabbi Akiva says if it's in the airspace, it's
like it's on the ground. Now, of course, even if it's like
if it's on the ground, there's one question: Is it in the
space of ארבע על ארבע? arba al arba? But still if it's
constantly moving, where's the הנחה? hanacha? Where did it stop? Okay, but
we're going to bracket that question. Rabbi Akiva's pretty drastic here. He
says it didn't stop, it's flying through, it wasn't even on the
ground, but once it's in that airspace, it's like it's on the
ground and therefore it's like you're חייב chayav because you brought it
into רשות הרבים. reshut harabim. Maybe you're even חייב chayav a second
time because then you take from רשות הרבים reshus harabim into another
רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid So if Rabbi Akiva can say that about
an object flying in mid-air, he would certainly say it about just
holding an object stationary in a place that's—like once it's in the
airspace of a place, it's like it's completely in that place itself
and you're חייב. chayav. Okay, that's what Rabbi Akiva says. ורבנן
סברי לא אמרינן קלוטה כמי שהונחה דמיא. verabanan savri lo amrinan kluta
k'mi she'huncha damya. So the גמרא Gemara says: למימרא דפשיטא ליה לרבא?
lemeimra d'pshita leh l'Rava? That sounds like it's clear to Rava that
דבקלוטה כמי שהונחה דמיא? de'bi'kluta k'mi she'huncha damya? The question is whether
something when it's absorbed in the airspace is like it's on the
ground. ובתוך עשרה פליגי. uvetoch asara paligi. Now the עמוד ב. And
they were arguing when it's under ten טפחים, tefachim. when it's within
the ten טפחים. tefachim. Because something is only in רשות הרבים, reshus
harabim right? The airspace is only ten טפחים. tefachim, But you can't
say that. והא מיבעיא בעי לה רבא. v'ha mibaya ba'i lah Rava.
Rava himself asked what—you know, raised that issue. What is this debate
about רבי עקיבא וחכמים Rabbi Akiva vechachamim about? דבעי רבא. deba'i Rava.
Rava asked: למטה מעשרה פליגי? lemata me'asara paligi? Are they arguing when
you threw it from one private domain to another and it went
through the airspace of רשות הרבים, reshus harabim, it was under ten
טפחים, tefachim which is considered the airspace of רשות הרבים. reshus harabim,
ובהא פליגי. uveha paligi. And this is a debate. רבי עקיבא סבר
קלוטה כמי שהונחה דמיא. Rabbi Akiva savar kluta k'mi she'huncha damya. Absorbed
is like it's placed on the ground, or caught in the airspace
is like it's on the ground, and therefore you did a הנחה.
hanacha. ורבנן סברי לא אמרינן קלוטה כמי שהונחה דמיא. verabanan savri lo
amrinan kluta k'mi she'huncha damya. And the Rabbis say we wouldn't say
that. That's one way of saying it. According to that, you'd be
right, you wouldn't need a הנחה hanacha according to Rabbi Akiva. Once
it's in the airspace, it's considered a הנחה. hanacha. That's one way
of saying it, which is very strict, which means that all, you
know, it's very easy to transgress הוצאה hotza'ah according to Rabbi Akiva
if you basically don't need a הנחה. hanacha. Once it's in the
airspace, it's like it's on the ground. That's one way of explaining
the debate. אבל למעלה מעשרה דברי הכל פטור. aval lemala me'asara divrei
hakol patur. If it's above ten טפחים tefachim. of the airspace of
רשות הרבים, reshus harabim דברי הכל פטור, divrei hakol patur, everybody would
say you're פטור. pator Because that's not רשות הרבים reshus harabim? over
ten טפחים. tefachim, That's one way of explaining, which is what we
just said. But there's another way of explaining. ודכולי עלמא v'dechulei alma
and within that, I would say, within that way, everybody would agree,
לא ילפינן זורק ממושיט. lo yalpinan zorek mimushit. We do not learn
throwing from extending, handing. What does this mean? Although you—everybody knows the
classic cases of הוצאה hotza'ah from private to public, public to private,
or ארבע אמות arba amot in a public domain, רשות הרבים. reshus
harabim, There's another case the גמרא Gemara says that's a very special
case, which just goes to show how somewhat arbitrary הוצאה hotza'ah is.
Another example תוספות Tosafot says about how it's מלאכה גרועה. melacha gru'ah.
It's sort of very arbitrary, it's not conceptual and abstract. And that
case is handing something. The גמרא Gemara says that basically one of
the ways they would operate in the—in the—in the מדבר, midbar, is
you have two wagons here
of the—of the לוים Leviyim carrying the beams of the ארון, Aron,
and you would extend something from one—you know, he would hand it
over from one wagon to the next. Now the wagon would be
a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid It would have like walls or
whatever it would— and handing it over and taking it whatever with
a רשות הרבים reshus harabim in the middle is actually another way
of doing הוצאה. hotza'ah. Who knew? Okay, but that actually is what
the גמרא Gemara says. That's considered a special case about משה, Moshe,
handing something over from one רשות היחיד reshus hayachid to another with
a רשות הרבים reshus harabim in the middle. Now that is a
classic case above ten טפחים, tefachim right? It's not so clear that
that would be true even when it would be within ten טפחים
tefachim, as the גמרא, Gemara תוספות Tosafot says קל וחומר kal vachomer
it would be, but it's not so clear. At least certainly it
applies for the case above ten טפחים, tefachim maybe the case below.
That's a special case of משה. Moshe. It also they have to
be considered to be like on the same side of רשות הרבים,
reshus harabim, not on opposite sides of רשות הרבים, reshus harabim which
so there's like a lot of criteria. But that's a special case
called משה. Moshe. So the question here is when you throw something
from one רשות היחיד reshus hayachid to another and someone is going
to say חייב, chayav, it's quite possibly that it has nothing to
do with like it stopped and then it started again. Maybe it's
חייב chayav because it is similar to this idea of handing the
beams over. So that's a very different way of explaining their debate.
So this is what רבא Rava asked. Is the debate under ten
טפחים tefachim and it's about whether it's considered to have stopped in
רשות הרבים reshus harabbim. and then start again and has to be
placed on the ground? But above ten טפחים tefachim. everybody would say
you're פטור pator because that's not the airspace of רשות הרבים? reshus
harabbim Or no, maybe it has nothing to do with stopping and
being placed down. Maybe it's about whether it's like this case of
משה Moshe of extending the beams. Okay, so let's read that inside.
So it says, wait, okay,
so the first way is it's about קלוטה כמי שהונחה. kluta k'mi
shehuncha.
אבל למעלה מעשרה דברי הכל פטור. aval l'ma'ala me'asara divrei hakol pator.
Above ten everybody says you're פטור pator. because that's not airspace of
רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim וכולי ולא ילפינן זורק ממשה. v'chulei v'lo yalpinan
zorek mi'Moshe. We do not learn throwing from the case of extending.
עוד אימא למעלה מעשרה פליגי. od eima l'ma'ala me'asara p'ligi. They argue
above ten. ובהא פליגי. uv'ha p'ligi. This is what they debate about.
It has nothing to do with קלוטה כמי שהונחה. kluta k'mi shehuncha.
דרבי עקיבא סבר ילפינן זורק ממשה, d'Rebbi Akiva savar yalpinan zorek mi'Moshe,
that we the same way when you extend the beams from one
רשות היחיד reshus hayachid, to another with a רשות הרבים reshus harabbim.
in the middle you're חייב chayav because that's called משה. Moshe. So
זורק zorek throwing is like doing the same thing. ורבנן סברי לא
ילפינן זורק ממשה. v'Rabbanan savri lo yalpinan zorek mi'Moshe. We don't learn
it. אבל למטה מעשרה, aval l'mata me'asara, below ten, דברי הכל חייב,
divrei hakol chayav,
maybe everybody would say you're חייב. chayav. מאי טעמא אמרינן קלוטה כמי
שהונחה דמי. mai ta'ama amrinan kluta k'mi shehuncha dami. We would say
caught is like it's on the ground. Or you could have said
the opposite. You could have said below ten everybody would say you're
פטור. Okay, anyway תוספות Tosafot sort of deals with that why it
went this way around and the other way and so on. But
nevertheless the גמרא Gemara says if we're looking for a position that
says that you don't when you that when you go by the
hand even though the hands are not four by four. Okay, now
we're realizing it's four by four טפחים. tefachim Okay, but you that's
the position we're looking for. You cannot quote רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva
about throwing something from one רשות היחיד reshus hayachid to another with
a רשות הרבים reshus harabbim in the middle. That could be a
very special case, it's learned out from משה Moshe and it has
nothing to do with a general rule of not requiring something to
be on a מקום makom of four by four.
Okay, so we're not going to sort of
put this all on רבי עקיבא. Rebbi Akiva. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says הא לא קשיא. ha lo kashya. No, maybe that's not
difficult. בתר דאיבעיא הדר איפשיטא ליה. batar d'ibaia hadar ipshita lei. Maybe
even after he raised the question that maybe it's about this idea
of משה, Moshe, maybe in the end he decided that that wasn't
what it was about.
דסבר רבי עקיבא קלוטה כמי שהונחה דמיא. d'savar Rebbi Akiva kluta k'mi
shehuncha damia. So maybe in the end he decided no, it's not
about משה, Moshe, it's within ten טפחים tefachim, and yes, רבי עקיבא
Rebbi Akiva says it doesn't have to be stationary, it doesn't have
to be on a מקום makom of four by four. Again the
חידוש chiddush about רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva is much more that you
don't need it to be on a מקום makom of four by
four. You know before we were discussing why do you even need
this idea of four by four if it's considered a מקום, makom,
is it considered a significant act? But רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva like
that at least it
was stationary, it was on something. Here רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva says
zooming through a place is like it stopped and started again and
so on. So that's much more radical. But yes, so maybe that's
what רמי בר חמא Rami bar Chama is based on. It's based
on this רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva idea. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says even if you say that, you can't go so that far.
Why? The גמרא Gemara says
ודילמא הנחה הוא דלא בעי עקירה בעי. v'dilma hanacha hu d'la bei
akira bei. Maybe only placing something down doesn't require four by four,
but picking it up he would still require that be picked up
from a מקום makom of four by four. So maybe you're חייב
chayav for bringing it into רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim but you're not
חייב chayav for taking it out of רשות הרבים reshut harabim, because
to be picking it up it has to start in a מקום
makom four by four. Now why should עקירה akira be more significant
than הנחה? hanacha? So תוספות Tosafot. here refers to the פסוק pasuk
he quoted
before, אל יצא איש ממקומו, al yeitzei ish mimkomo, that if we
learn that to mean don't take the object from its מקום, makom,
it starts with the idea of the removal from the מקום. makom.
So that has more of a demand of a significant מקום makom
of four by four. And here in our משנה it's clear that
even the uprooting didn't require four by four because the עני ani
took from the hands of the בעל הבית baal habayit that wasn't
four by four, right? And therefore it's going to be a space.
What about רש"י? Rashi What?
Yes, רש"י doesn't really explain but that you can't prove. Maybe רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva does not say both don't require four by four.
Maybe the עקירה akira might also be more important because it's the
beginning of the act so that gives greater significance to the act
when it starts in a certain way. So the גמרא says even
if רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is saying it doesn't have to A
be stationary and B be on a certain size space, it's just
in air, it's not on the ground, it's just in this zone
zone. Maybe again you cannot learn that for both עקירה akira and
הנחה. hanacha. Maybe only for one of them, maybe he's only saying
that stringency for הנחה. hanacha. Yes.
Does רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva ever give an explanation for why he
believes that the air and the earth are...? No, no.
And anyway, this is just an abstraction of רבא, Rava, it might
have nothing to do with קלוטה, kluta, it might have to do
with motion then. I should also say another explanation which isn't about
הנחה hanacha being more עקירה akira making more demands than הנחה hanacha
but about the concept of קלוטה. kluta. קלוטה kluta sort of means
like you, you like ערי מקלט, arei miklat, you've absorbed somebody, you've
saved somebody, like the object has entered in when it goes into
רשות reshus? הרבים. That transition, that it came into the air space,
might make it say, oh, welcome ברוך הבא. baruch haba. So now
you come into the air space, it's like you're here. Okay, as
opposed to leaving, right? That's, that's not like that, it's a different
thing. It's the act of coming in which makes it considered to
be present. Okay, so that, you know, the קלוטה, kluta, the act
of being קלוט kolat is when it comes into the space, not
when it leaves the space. Anyway, that's what the גמרא says, you
can't prove from רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva although he has it in
mid-air and it's not that it's in the space, maybe that's only
for putting down, not for removing. So we don't know the idea
that you don't need it in either case. I should say by
the way about this issue that four by four means טפחים, tefachim.
the גמרא is clear about this because Michael mentioned again in a,
you know, this possibility and the גמרא will say a possibility, maybe
the person just caught it on his hand, maybe like spread out
his like, you know, apron and it's in an, you know, and
the thing is in some, and he caught it in an apron
or something of that sort. So clearly again an indication that we're
talking about four by four טפחים. tefachim. You don't have an apron
that's six feet by six feet. Okay. So we're talking about a
space that's about a foot by a foot although for a person
it goes by אמה amah and אמה amah as I said sometimes
is a size of significance of a certain type of a place
to be in, you know, sense of it's a, the space of
a thing is four by four טפחים. Okay so now the גמרא
continues in the following way.
אלא אמר רב יוסף, Ela amar Rav Yosef, הא מני ha manni
who is this? רבי. Rabbi. It's רבי. Rabbi. Okay, היי רבי, hi
Rabbi, which רבי? Rabbi? אילימא הא רבי, Ileima ha Rabbi, the following
רבי. Rabbi. דתניא Detanya we taught in
a ברייתא. Baraita. זרק ונח אגבי זיז כל שהוא, Zarak venach agabi
ziz kol shehu, רבי מחייב וחכמים פוטרין. Rabbi mechayev vachachamim potrin. This
seems to be a perfect proof. You threw something and it landed
on a little protrusion. Okay, you threw it presumably from רשות reshus
הרבים to רשות היחיד and it, it didn't hit the ground, it
just got, it stuck on a little, you know, on a little
protrusion and the thing is suspended on this protrusion. רבי Rabbi says
you're still חייב chayav and חכמים chachamim say you're exempt. So that
seems to be exactly the question: do you need this idea
of מקום ארבע makom arba or not? Okay. התם, so the גמרא
says not necessarily. התם כדבעינן למימר לקמן כידאביי. Hasham kidebayeina lemeimar lekaman
kideAbaye. No, there we're going to reframe it like
אביי. Abaye. דאמר אביי, De'amar Abaye, אביי Abaye says הכא באילן העומד
ברשות היחיד ונופו נוטה לרשות הרבים. hacha be'ilan ha'omed bereshus hayachid venofov
noto lereshus harabbim. We're talking about, now this gets complicated, we're talking
about a tree that it, you hit a tree and you got
it on a branch of a tree. That's a little כל שהוא
kol shehu protrusion. But where is the tree? The root is in
רשות היחיד, the branch extends to רשות הרבים וזרק ונח על נופו.
vezarak venach al nofo. You threw it and it got stuck on
a branch.
And where were you?
You were in the
רשות הרבים. רבי Rabbi סבר, savar, one minute, אמרינן שדי נופו בתר
עיקרו. amrinan shadi nofo basar ikaro. רבי Rabbi says we say throw
the branch towards the root, towards the trunk, I should say trunk
probably better. ורבנן סברי לא אמרינן שדי נופו בתר עיקרו. Verabbanan savari
lo amrinan shadi nofo basar ikaro. You don't throw the branch towards
the trunk. Now what the heck does all of this mean? So
basically there's,
there's a debate רש"י תוספות. Tosafot תוספות Tosafot explains it in a
much more פשט, peshat, you know, if you say that the trunk
is here and the branch is there and it hit the branch.
It seems odd, obviously the question you're asking is, what's the question
you're asking? You put something, something's trunk is here and the branch
is in רשות היחיד and the branch is in רשות הרבים and
you threw it and it hit and got stuck on the branch.
What should be the question you ask?
Did you throw it to another
רשות?
Which רשות is it considered to be in? Where the branch is
or where the trunk is? Sort of like the hand that's extended
and so on, right? So that's what the language sounds like also.
Do you throw the branch to the trunk or not? So that's
the way תוספות explains it and the issue here is that if
you threw it on the branch of, if you threw it on
the branch or if you threw it in רשות הרבים it hit
the, it got stuck on the branch but it's considered to follow
in רשות היחיד *Reshus HaYachid* and therefore you're חייב *chayav* for taking
it to רשות הרבים *Reshus HaRabim* even though it's physically right now
one minute in a רשות הרבים *Reshus HaRabim*. Now how does that
address the issue? So that's based on a later גמרא *Gemara*, that's
how it's going to explain what the debate is, whether it's going
to be considered to be in רשות היחיד *Reshus HaYachid* or רשות
הרבים *Reshus HaRabim*. How does that address our case? Well, it addresses
our case because
רבי Rebbi *Rebbi* actually, because let me just check one thing about
תוספות *Tosafot*.
Right, so תוספות *Tosafot* actually says that that issue of which zone
it's in is really the issue of the גמרא *Gemara* later. We're
mentioning it here because that's how we frame it later, but that's
not really what's of interest to us right now. To us, what's
of interest is to make it considered like it's where the trunk
is as opposed to where the branch is. But what is of
interest is if the branch follows the trunk then that means we're
giving significance to the trunk. And if the trunk is four by
four טפחים *tefachim* then it does not matter that the branch is
not because it's on the branch it's like it's on the trunk.
The same way it's like it's in a רשות היחיד *Reshus HaYachid*,
it's like it's on the trunk and therefore that's your body itself
but your body also is not four by four. That's the thing.
I mean it's not doesn't work. What?
Your body I mean it's like a foot by a
foot, anyway it doesn't work. Okay, so תוספות *Tosafot* says the basic
point is don't bring me a proof from that case. That case
has to do with branch and trunk and the idea is that
it follows the trunk and if the trunk is four טפחים *tefachim*
that's why you're חייב *chayav* but normally it's not enough that it's
on a little space. Okay, that's the way תוספות *Tosafot* says it.
רש"י *Rashi* says, and it doesn't fit the language so well, רש"י
*Rashi* says no it's not considered in רשות היחיד *Reshus HaYachid*, it's
considered in רשות הרבים *Reshus HaRabim* but you threw it four אמות
*amos* in רשות הרבים *Reshus HaRabim*. What does it mean throw the
branch after the trunk? It really means according to רש"י *Rashi* throw
the trunk after the branch, I mean because it's connected to the
trunk that gives it a significance as if it's four by four
טפחים *tefachim*. Okay, that gives it, meaning it's not like we look
at it in the place of the trunk but that gives significance
to this place because part of the object is big and wide.
Like imagine for example you had a table that was four by
four טפחים *tefachim* and you had a little I don't know like
an extension or whatever and it was on the extension. Okay, but
it's connected to the whole thing, it's on a space of four
by four טפחים *tefachim*. And רש"י *Rashi* completely ignores the idea of
which zone is it in. But whether רש"י *Rashi* or תוספות *Tosafot*,
they all agree the relevant point here is because the base has
four by four טפחים *tefachim* therefore even the branch is significant and
that's not relevant to our case where we're not saying you don't
need four by four, we're saying it counts as four by four
because you have it in the base. Okay, which is not true
about a person, a person is not a foot by a foot.
I hope not, otherwise they'd be pretty wide to be a foot
by a foot. Okay anyway so that's what we say. So that's
what it's about. אלא *Ella* so you can't bring a proof from
there, there it's because the trunk has four by four טפחים *tefachim*.
אלא הא רבי *Ella ha Rebbi*, the following רבי *Rebbi*, דתניא *detanya*,
זרק מרשות הרבים לרשות הרבים ורשות היחיד באמצע *zarak mereshus harabim lereshus
harabim ureshus hayachid be'emtza*, it's the reverse of the previous case. You
threw from a public to a public with a private domain in
the middle. Now that cannot be this idea of משה *Moshe* of
the beams. The beams is very specifically private to private with public
in the middle. Here you did public to public with private in
the middle. So you basically threw something through one guy's window, went
in the window, out the other window and it landed in the
opposite street. Okay so wait a minute, what's the story there?
So רבי מחייב *Rebbi mechayiv*, רבי *Rebbi* says you have transgressed, וחכמים
פוטרין *veChachamim potrin*, the sages say you're exempt because it didn't stop,
it didn't rest, you're exempt. So you see if רבי *Rebbi* says
you're חייב *chayav* even without stopping, that's like you do not need
it to be on מקום ארבעה *makom arba*, it's like רבי עקיבא
Rebbi Akiva *Rebbi Akiva*, but it's now not based on this whole
beam idea. So you really, it seems that you don't need it
to be on a space, even in air space it's enough. So
the גמרא *Gemara* says, דאמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל *de'amar Rav Yehuda
amar Shmuel*, מחייב היה רבי שתים *mechayiv haya Rebbi shtayim*. Now back
to your point before, you said maybe it's only for resting you
don't need the space but maybe you need the space for taking
it out, for עקירה *akira*. No, because we have a statement in
the name of שמואל *Shmuel* that רבי *Rebbi* says you get two
transgressions, one for bringing it in the house and the other for
bringing it out of the house. So you see he doesn't need
there to be a space four by four טפחים *tefachim* either for
putting it down or for picking it up, for עקירה *akira*. אחת
משום הוצאה ואחת משום הכנסה *achas mishum hotza'ah ve'achas mishum hachnasah*. אמר
לא בעי עקירה דלא הנחה אגבי מקום ארבעה *amar
lo ba'ei akira delo hanacha agabi makom arba*. You don't need it
to be for either the act of picking it up or the
act of putting it down, you don't need it to be on
a four by four טפחים *tefachim* space, you just need it to
be in the airspace. Okay the גמרא *Gemara* says you can't say
that. הא איתמר עלה *ha itmar alah*, no we said about this,
רבא ושמואל דאמרי תרווייהו *Rava uShmuel de'amri tarvaihu*, רבא *Rava* and שמואל
*Shmuel* both said לא מחייב רבי אלא ברשות היחיד מקורה *lo mechayiv
Rebbi ella bireshus hayachid mekura*, דאמרינן ביתא כמאן דמליא דמי *de'amrinan beisa
keman demalya dami*, אבל שאינו מקורה לא *aval she'eino mekura lo*. רבי
*Rebbi* only says it if it went through a house, a private
domain with a roof because when it has a roof it's like
it's filled but if it does not have a roof it would
not count, which means
it would not work for a
In our case, remember you also have taking from the hand and
putting in the hand of the עני, ani but רבי only says
this idea that it doesn't need a space only for things that
are in a house. What is this idea that a house is
like it's full is not exactly clear, but I think if you
go back to the רבי עקיבא phrase of קלוטה כמי שהונחה, keluta
k'mi shehuncha, you can understand. A house really holds its possessions. Something
without a roof, even if it's in walls, its possessions are really
seen to be held by something that's not only surrounded by walls
but also has a roof. So when you throw it in a
house, it's held by the house, it's like it's put down, when
it flies out it's like it's removed, it's like it's fully there
even without four by four. But if it doesn't have a roof,
and if it's in a רשות הרבים, which doesn't have a roof,
then it is going to require four by four and we still
do not have an answer to our question about the hands of
the עני and the בעל הבית, ba'al habayit, which we will see
that, God willing, on Monday.